Guide to the J. M. Barrie Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1876–1954; Series II; 16.5; 35 boxes
  - Plays and Other Scripts
    - La Politesse
      - Typescript, with autograph revisions, circa 1918 (Box 45, Folder 955)
        Titled "The Politest Nation." In brown paper wrappers.
    - The Professor's Love Story
      A three-act play produced December 19, 1892, at the Star Theatre, New York, and June 25, 1894, at the Comedy Theatre, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1892 (Box 45, Folder 956)
        Pages 21-26 of Act III wanting and supplied in typescript.
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections and additions, circa 1892 (Box 45, Folder 957)
        Acts I-III; in gray paper wrappers.
    - Punch, circa 1906 (Box 45, Folder 958)
      Typescript of a one-act play with note in an unidentified hand: "Sent to Miss Maude Adams by request of J. M. Barrie." Performed April 5, 1906, at the Comedy Theatre, London, as part of a triple bill. George Bernard Shaw is represented in the character "New Man." Accompanied by one leaf of autograph manuscript numbered page 5½. In gray paper wrappers.
    - Quality Street
      Play produced on November 11, 1901, at the Knickerbocker Theatre, New York.
      - "Quotation and Autographs from 'Quality Street'", 1902 (Box 45, Folder 959)
        Quotations from the play written and signed by the cast in the 1902 production at the Vaudeville Theatre, London, including Seymour Hicks and Ellaline Terriss.
      - Score for a string quintet, circa 1901 (Box 45, Folder 960)
        Manuscript, in unidentified hand. Inscribed on title page: "Score String Quintett 'Quality Street' Music by Wm. Furst Empire Theatre. N.Y. City."
    - A Real Play at Last, undated (Box 45, Folder 961)
      A one-act play; typescript with manuscript corrections; in red paper wrappers.
    - The Real Thing at Last, circa 1916 (Box 45, Folder 962)
      Carbon typescript for a silent film, a satire of Macbeth as if it had been performed as an American film. It was shown on March 7, 1916, at the London Coliseum during a benefit to raise funds for the Y.M.C.A. Titled "Film" and "Macbeth" on cover and "Film" on title page. In gray paper wrappers.
    - Reconstructing the Crime. A Strange Play in Seven Scenes
      Produced February 16, 1917, at the Palace Theatre, London.
      - Typescript, initialed, with autograph revisions, circa 1917 (Box 45, Folder 963)
        Each scene individually bound in brown paper wrappers; Scene 4 is a ballet titled "The Origin of Harlequin."
      - Typescript with manuscript revisions in an unidentified hand, circa 1917 (Box 45, Folder 964)
        All scenes bound together; Scene 4 (ballet) has been cut out. Accompanied by one leaf of typed directions for stage business. In a gray paper wrappers.
    - Richard Savage
      A four-act play, written in collaboration with H. B. Marriott Watson and produced only once, on April 16, 1891, at a matinee at Criterion Theatre, London. Barrie's account of the production appears in Chapter XXIII of The Greenwood Hat.
      - "Scenario of Richard Savage", circa 1891 (Box 46, Folder 965)
        Autograph notes for a three-act version of the play.
      - Autograph manuscript, with corrections, circa 1891 (Box 46, Folder 966)
        Autograph inscription on first page: "Though all in my own handwriting this was a joint work by H. B. Marriott Watson and myself. The first thing of mine produced on the stage, and then only once at a matinee at Criterion Theatre." The names of the characters in Act I differ from those in the following acts. Accompanied by a single sheet of autograph manuscript which corresponds to page 12 of Act II.
      - Stage play license, 1891 March 24 (Box 46, Folder 967)
        Engraved form permitting the Criterion Theatre produce the play Richard Savage; filled in on both sides in manuscript and signed by the Lord Chamberlain (Edward Bootle-Wilbraham, Earl of Lathom).
    - Rosalind: A Little Comedy
      A one-act play produced October 14, 1912, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, 1910 April 18 (Box 46, Folder 968)
        Dated in typist's stamp on title page. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 969)
      - Four typescripts with manuscript revisions in unidentified hands, [1912] (Box 46, Folder 970)
        Three typescripts are in blue paper covers, one in yellow. The typescripts are labelled Prompt Copy, Mrs. Page, Mrs. Quickly, and Charles. The Prompt Copy is accompanied by a stage plan.
      - Two typescript sides for "Mrs. Quickly" and "Charles", [1912] (Box 46, Folder 971)
        Both annotated in Irene Vanbrugh's hand "Property of Irene Vanbrugh. 3 Dudley House Westmoreland St. W1." In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript with manuscript revisions in Irene Vanbrugh's hand, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 972)
        Accompanied by a copy of four leaves of the text (18, 19, 20-22, 22-23) in the hand of Irene Vanbrugh. Bound in green morocco with author, title and "I.V. 1912" gold-stamped on the front cover, and Vanbrugh's signature on the first front flyleaf.
      - Typescript with manuscript revisions in Irene Vanbrugh's hand, [1912] (Box 46, Folder 973)
        Accompanied by six leaves of manuscript (in an unidentified hand) of lighting plots, property plots and stage sets, and seven telegrams addressed to Irene Vanbrugh in an envelope inscribed "'Rosalind' Property Telegrams."
      - Typescript with manuscript revisions in Irene Vanbrugh's hand, [1912] (Box 46, Folder 974)
        In a gray wrapper, with Elizabeth Marbury's printed sticker on the front cover.
      - Typescript of a scenario by Peter Lambda, undated (Box 46, Folder 975)
        Accompanied by one leaf with a poem in an unidentified hand.
    - Rosy Rapture: The Pride of the Beauty Chorus
      A revue in seven scenes produced March 22, 1915, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
      - Typescript, circa 1915 (Box 46, Folder 976)
        Cover title: "Revue." In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, circa 1915 (Box 46, Folder 977)
        Cover and title page title: "Burlesque." In gray paper wrappers.
    - Seven Women
      A one-act comedy produced April 7, 1917, at the New Theatre, London. Seven Women is a variation of Act I of The Adored One, published as The Legend of Leonora in The Works of J. M. Barrie (New York, 1941), v. 17.
      - Typescripts with autograph revisions, circa 1917 (Box 46, Folder 978)
        Three typescripts, all with autograph revisions. Typescript 1 varies from typescripts 2 and 3 which are the same as the version published in The Plays of J. M. Barrie (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1928). In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, 1917 (Box 46, Folder 979)
        Irene Vanbrugh's copy, bound in green morocco with author, title, and "I.V. 1917" stamped in gold on the front cover.
    - Shakespeare's Legacy, [1916] (Box 47, Folder 980)
      Typescript, with autograph revisions, of a one-act play produced April 14, 1916, at the Drury Lane Theatre, London, for a Shakespeare tercentenary celebration. It was privately printed by Clement Shorter in London, May 9, 1916. In gray paper wrappers.
    - Shall We Join the Ladies? An Uncomfortable Play
      A one-act play produced May 27, 1921, at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1921 (Box 47, Folder 981)
        Varies from the text published in The Black Cap, New Stories of Murder and Mystery, compiled by Cynthia Asquith (London: Hutchinson, 1927).
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1921 (Box 47, Folder 982)
        One leaf with the page number 15.
    - A Slice of Life: An Advanced Drama
      A one-act play produced June 7, 1910, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, circa 1910 (Box 47, Folder 983)
        Initialed, with note: "for a special performance." Cover and title page title: "Drama." In brown paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, 1912 (Box 47, Folder 984)
        Includes pen and ink sketch of stage setting with property list. Clipped cast list from Empire Theatre performance (January 29, 1912), starring Ethel and John Barrymore, and Hattie Williams, is pasted on front flyleaf. Bound.
    - "The Stanway Plays"
      A group of plays written by Barrie and produced privately at Stanway, the Gloucestershire home of Hugo Richard Charteris, the 11th Earl of Wemyss, and father of author Cynthia Asquith, Barrie's secretary and friend. Cast members included the Asquith boys and their cousins.
      - "Barrie's dialogue acted by Michael Simon at Stanway August 1925", 1925 August (Box 47, Folder 985)
        Accompanied by an envelope inscribed by Cynthia Asquith.
      - The Wheel
        A three-act play produced at Stanway, April 18, 1927, for the family and guests of Lord Wemyss. He and his grandchildren are the characters and actors in the play. Part of the text consists of dialogue adapted from Shakespeare's plays As You Like It, Romeo and Juliet, and Macbeth. The three versions present are titled differently.
        - "Tomorrow and Tomorrow and Tomorrow (The Spinning Wheel)", [1926] (Box 47, Folder 986)
          Autograph manuscript; last leaves of the play are missing.
        - "The Stanway Ghost: A Play for Eight Children and their Grandpa", [1926] (Box 47, Folder 987)
          Typescript with gray paper front wrapper.
        - "The Wheel", 1926 (Box 47, Folder 988-989)
          Four typescripts with autograph revisions, and some manuscript revisions in Cynthia Asquith's hand in Typescript IV. Two scripts dated November 26, 1926; two scripts marked "Prompt Copy" are undated. In gray paper wrappers. Accompanied by performance program printed by the Curwen Press, Christmas 1926.
      - Where was Simon? Or The Secret of the Pyramid
        A five-act play produced on January 16, 1926.
        - Autograph manuscript, signed, [1925] (Box 47, Folder 990)
          Inscribed on first front flyleaf: "Cynthia Asquith." Bound in green morocco by Douglas Cockerell & Son; signed "DC & Son 1929."
        - Typescript with autograph revisions and manuscript notes in an unidentified hand., [1925] (Box 47, Folder 991)
          In brown paper wrappers. Accompanied by a printed program for the play.
      - The Yellow Week at Stanway. A Record of Fair Women and Brainy Men
        A film documenting a week's activities shared by Barrie and his guests at Stanway; it was shown privately in London on October 11, 1923.
        - Typescripts, 1923 (Box 47, Folder 992)
          Three scenarios with autograph revisions and manuscript revisions in an unidentified hand.
        - Notes and titles, 1923 (Box 47, Folder 993)
          Autograph notes for the scenario accompanied by typescript titles, with manuscript notes in an unidentified hand, to be used with the scenario.
    - The Story of her Life: A Fifteen Minute Sketch, undated (Box 47, Folder 994)
      Autograph manuscript of a play, incomplete. Characters in the play are Gilbert Hare, Gerald du Maurier, and Lady Tree.
    - "Der Tag," or The Tragic Man
      A one-act play produced December 21, 1914, at the Coliseum, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1914 (Box 48, Folder 995)
        The leaves are numbered 1, 2, 3, and 17.
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, initialed, circa 1914 (Box 48, Folder 996)
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, circa 1914 (Box 48, Folder 997)
      - Typescript, circa 1914 (Box 48, Folder 998)
    - [Taming of the Shrew]
      Notes, scripts, and ideas for film and stage productions based on Shakespeare's play.
      - Autograph manuscript of part of a play, circa 1915 (Box 48, Folder 999)
        Titled "Taming." The leaves are numbered 5-7 and [1]-14. Accompanied by four leaves of autograph manuscript notes for the play.
      - Autograph notes for a play, undated (Box 48, Folder 1000)
        Titled "Shakes."
      - Autograph notes for a film, 1920 January 9 (Box 48, Folder 1001)
        The leaves are numbered 31, 32, 33, 33½, and 34.
      - Autograph notes for a film, circa 1920 (Box 48, Folder 1002)
        Titled on first page: "A Comedy. For the Film."
      - Typescript notes for a film, circa 1920 (Box 48, Folder 1003)
        Titled on title page: "A Comedy. For the Film."
    - Temperament, undated (Box 48, Folder 1004)
      Autograph notes for a play about an actor.
    - The Twelve-Pound Look
      A one-act play produced March 1, 1910, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, [1910] (Box 48, Folder 1005)
        The first two leaves of a script, accompanied by the first leaf of another version of the play.
      - Typescript, signed, with autograph corrections, circa 1910 (Box 48, Folder 1006)
        Autograph inscription on title page: "Property of J. M. Barrie" and "The Twelve Pound Look"; label on cover and stamp on title page of the British Drama League, London. In brown paper wrappers.
    - The Wedding Guest
      A four-act play produced in September 27, 1900, at the Garrick Theatre, London. The text was published in a supplement to the Fortnightly Review in December 1900.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1900 (Box 48, Folder 1007)
      - Typescript, circa 1900 (Box 48, Folder 1008)
        Four acts in carbon copy, with cover title: "The Two Kinds of Women " In gray paper wrappers.
    - A Well-Remembered Voice
      A one-act play produced June 23, 1918, at Wyndham's Theatre, London. Published in Barrie's Echoes of the War (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1918).
      - Typescripts, circa 1918 (Box 48, Folder 1009)
        Five typescripts with autograph revisions.
      - Typescripts, circa 1918 (Box 48, Folder 1010)
        Sides for the characters Mr. Don, Mrs. Don, Laura Bell, Mr. Rogers, Another, and Major Armitage. In brown paper wrappers.
    - What Every Woman Knows
      A four-act play produced September 3, 1908, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
      - Typescript with autograph and manuscript corrections and additions, circa 1908 (Box 49, Folder 1011)
        Charles Frohman's name is stamped on the preliminary leaves of Acts II, III, and IV. Autograph corrections and additions in Acts II and III, and manuscript corrections in an unidentified hand in Acts II, III, and IV. In green linen wrappers.
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections and additions, circa 1908 (Box 49, Folder 1012)
        Pasted on the verso of the preliminary leaf of Act I is the autograph signature of Maude Adams. Accompanied by a second copy of Act II with corrections and additions in an unidentified hand. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, 1925 (Box 49, Folder 1013)
        R. Golding Bright's name is stamped on the preliminary leaves of each act with the date October 27, 1925, within a second stamp of Marshall's Typewriting & Translations. Bound in green cloth.
      - Autograph notes, circa 1908 (Box 49, Folder 1014)
      - Typescript with manuscript corrections, undated (Box 49, Folder 1015)
        In gray covers, each stamped "From Charles Frohman, Empire Theatre Building, Broadway & 40th Street, New York" with "M. A." in ink on each cover label.
        Gift of New York Public Library.
    - When the War Is to End, circa 1915 (Box 49, Folder 1016)
      Typescript with autograph revisions. Irene Vanbrugh, Lillian Braithwaite and Nelson Keys are the principal characters in the skit. In gray paper wrappers.
    - Why? A Conundrum, 1914 (Box 49, Folder 1017)
      Typescript of a skit produced privately July 3, 1914, at the Savoy Theatre for a party given by Barrie for famous people in the literary, theatrical, and political world. A. E. W. Mason is the subject of the skit.
    - Women Spoil Everything
      A one-act play.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1915 (Box 49, Folder 1018)
        Two leaves have double numbers, 15-16 and 17-18. Autograph note on the first page: "This is no good and is never to be acted J.M.B."
      - Typescript, circa 1915 (Box 49, Folder 1019)
    - Untitled plays
      - Three-act play set in Venice during the seventeenth century, undated (Box 49, Folder 1020)
        Typescript with manuscript corrections; characters include Galeotto, Eugenio, Bartolo, Drusio, and Camilla.
      - Act II of a play set at the "British Legation in Brugia", undated (Box 49, Folder 1021)
        Typescript with manuscript corrections and additions; characters include Rodney Lydyard, Reginald Rankin, Sir Charles Garmilow, Lady Garmilow, and Belvaney. In brown paper wrappers.
  - Prefaces
    Arranged chronologically.
    - For The Boy Who Did Grow Up, 1919 (Box 50, Folder 1022)
      Autograph manuscript foreword published in The Boy Who Did Grow Up, by Newman Flower (London: Cassell and Company, 1919). Accompanied by three autograph letters, signed, to Thomas Moffat Young (1918-1919) and a facsimile of the foreword clipped from the London Sunday Times (1919).
    - For The Young Visiters, 1919 (Box 50, Folder 1023)
      Autograph manuscript published in The Young Visiters, or, Mr. Salteenas Plan, by Daisy Ashford (London: Chatto & Windus, 1919).
    - For Theatre Street: the Reminiscences of Tamara Karsavina, 1930 (Box 50, Folder 1024)
      Autograph manuscript; varies from the text published in Theatre Street: the Reminiscences of Tamara Karsavina (London: W. Heinemann, Ltd., 1930).
    - For Antony (Viscount Knebworth): A Record of Youth, 1935 (Box 50, Folder 1025)
      Autograph manuscript and typescript, signed, of a preface published in Antony (Viscount Knebworth): a Record of Youth, by Victor Alexander George Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of Lytton (London: Peter Davies, 1935). Accompanied by an envelope addressed to Peter Davies and postmarked October 26, 1935.
  - Speeches
    Several texts present were published in M'Connachie and J.M.B.: Speeches by J. M. Barrie, with a preface by Hugh Walpole (London: Peter Davies Limited, 1938). Texts of some other speeches are filed with Press Association correspondence in Series I, Box 13.
    - "Miss Trevelyan at the O.P. Club", 1908 (Box 50, Folder 1026)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech written by Barrie and delivered by Hilda Trevelyan at the Annual Dinner of The O.P. Club, London. Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Carl Hentschel to Hilda Trevelyan dated September 23, 1908; a printed program for the dinner, autographed by Carl Hentschel and Max Pemberton; and a typed copy of the speech.
    - Draft of a speech possibly delivered while visiting the United States, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 1027)
      Autograph manuscript
    - For the unveiling of the Recording Angel memorial in St Stephen's Porch, Westminster Hall, 1921 (Box 50, Folder 1028)
      Autograph manuscript accompanied by an envelope with note in the hand of Cynthia Asquith: "Speech written by J. M. Barrie for the then Prince of Wales (Duke of Windsor) on the occasion of his unveiling of House of Commons War Memorial; but NOT delivered!"
    - To the Critics' Circle, 1922 (Box 50, Folder 1029)
      Autograph manuscript notes for a speech to the Critics' Circle, delivered May 26, 1922, at the Savoy Hotel.
    - Rectorial address, the University of St Andrews, 1922 May 3 (Box 50, Folder 1030)
      Autograph manuscript, signed and dated April 19, 1922; inscribed on page 1: "To Mrs Irvine with affectionate regards from J M Barrie." Accompanied by a brown envelope inscribed in hand of Cynthia Asquith: "Manuscript of Address J.M.B. Adelphi Terrace House May 15th 1922." Published as Courage (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1922).
    - "Rhodes Scholars", 1928 June 20 (Box 50, Folder 1031)
      Autograph manuscript.
    - "Mary Queen of Scots Bazaar at Jedburgh", 1928 October 11 (Box 50, Folder 1032)
    - "Society of Authors Dinner", 1928 November 28 (Box 50, Folder 1033)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech delivered to the Incorporated Society of Authors, Playwrights, and Composers.
    - "Scottish Corporation Dinner", 1928 November 30 (Box 50, Folder 1034)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a speech delivered to the Royal Scottish Corporation.
    - "Newspaper Press Fund", 1929 April 23 (Box 50, Folder 1035)
    - "Royal Literary Fund", 1930 May 9 (Box 50, Folder 1036)
    - "Kirriemuir", 1930 June 7 (Box 50, Folder 1037)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech delivered at the opening of the cricket pavilion in Kirriemuir on the occasion of receipt of the Freedom of Kirriemuir. Accompanied by a typed transcript and carbon copy, both with autograph revisions.
    - "Installation as Chancellor of Edinburgh University", 1930 October 25 (Box 50, Folder 1038)
      Autograph manuscript of the address delivered on his installation to the office of chancellor, with note: "To Cynthia from JMB." Varies from the text published in London, 1930. Accompanied by page nine of another autograph manuscript copy of the speech.
    - To the Edinburgh University Club of London, 1930 November 12 (Box 50, Folder 1039)
      Autograph manuscript accompanied by one leaf of autograph notes.
    - For the opening of the Edinburgh Health Exhibition, 1932 January 27 (Box 50, Folder 1040)
      Autograph notes for a speech delivered January 27, 1932, at the Waverly Market.
    - "Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh", 1932 January 27 (Box 50, Folder 1041)
      Autograph manuscript of speech delivered in aid of the Edinburgh Royal Infirmary, accompanied fragments of other drafts and a leaf of notes for the speech.
    - To the Grant Institute of Geology, University of Edinburgh, 1932 January 28 (Box 50, Folder 1042)
      Autograph manuscript, accompanied by one leaf of autograph manuscript notes for the speech.
    - "Institute of Journalists Edinburgh", 1932 January 30 (Box 50, Folder 1043)
      Two autograph manuscripts, accompanied by one leaf of autograph notes and three incomplete autograph copies of page 4.
    - To the Authors' Club Dinner, 1932 December 12 (Box 50, Folder 1044)
      Autograph manuscript, accompanied by a typed copy with autograph revisions and nine pages of autograph notes.
    - For Elisabeth Bergner, [1934] (Box 50, Folder 1045)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech written for Bergner to deliver on the last night of her performance in Margaret Kennedy's Escape Me Never. In the speech Bergner said she would appear next in a new play without a heroine by Sir James Barrie [ The Boy David ].
    - "Australian Cricketeers", 1934 May 31 (Box 50, Folder 1046)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech delivered at a dinner honoring the Australian Cricket Team and given by the Surrey County Cricket Club, Carpenters' Hall. Accompanied by three typescripts of the speech with autograph revisions in two of them. Varies from the text published in M'Connachie and J. M. B.
    - "Hand", circa 1935 (Box 50, Folder 1047)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech in which Barrie tells how he lost the use of his right hand and how he learned to use his left hand; the speech ends with a toast to Dr. A. Logan Turner.
    - "Our Rogue in Porcelain", 1935 (Box 50, Folder 1048)
      Autograph manuscript and typescript of a speech given at a lunch on March 5, 1935, to celebrate the jubilee of Marie Tempest. Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Barrie to George W. Bishop (March 26, 1935).
    - "Drama", circa 1936 (Box 50, Folder 1049)
      Autograph manuscript of a speech in which Barrie reminisces about George Bernard Shaw.
    - "Speech Day at Bedford School", undated (Box 50, Folder 1050)
      Autograph manuscript, accompanied by autograph notes.
  - Other Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - The Allahakbarrie Book of Broadway Cricket for 1899 (Box 50, Folder 1051)